<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Relation of the passages in the battel at sea, between the fleet of England, and the United Neitherlands [sic] collected according to the charge &amp; order of the Lords States General, dated June 24/14 [sic] 1666 / by the Lords De Witt, councill-pensioner, Vrybergen, Van der Hoolck, Kan &amp; Gerlacius, deputies &amp; plenipotentiaries of  the States General, at present beeing in the VVielings, for expediteing [sic] &amp; over the imploy of the foresaid Neitherlands [sic] fleet ; translated faithfully out of the Dutch copy, &amp; published for the undeceiving of the English nation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92373</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R856A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42557</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282320</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282320</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150219</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92373)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150219)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2236:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Relation of the passages in the battel at sea, between the fleet of England, and the United Neitherlands [sic] collected according to the charge &amp; order of the Lords States General, dated June 24/14 [sic] 1666 / by the Lords De Witt, councill-pensioner, Vrybergen, Van der Hoolck, Kan &amp; Gerlacius, deputies &amp; plenipotentiaries of  the States General, at present beeing in the VVielings, for expediteing [sic] &amp; over the imploy of the foresaid Neitherlands [sic] fleet ; translated faithfully out of the Dutch copy, &amp; published for the undeceiving of the English nation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[The Hague? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed Anno 1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Four Days' Battle, 1666.</term>
               <term>Anglo-Dutch War, 1664-1667.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150219:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION Of the Paſſages in the BATTEL at SEA, Between the Fleet of ENGLAND And the United NEITHERLANDS; Collected according to the charge &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Lords States General:</hi> Dated June 24/14 1666.</p>
            <p>By the Lords DE WITT, Councill-Penſioner, VRYBER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GEN, VAN DER HOOLCK, KAN &amp; GERLACIUS, Deputies &amp; Plenipotentiaries of the <hi>States General,</hi> at preſent beeing in the <hi>VVielings,</hi> for expediteing &amp; over the imploy of the foreſaid <hi>Neitherlands Fleet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated faithfully out of the Dutch Copy, &amp; published for the undeceiving of the English Nation.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
               <p>PVGNO PRO PATRIA</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed Anno 1666.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150219:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150219:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:150219:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150219:3"/>
            <head>A Relation of the Paſſages in the Battel at Sea, betwixt the Fleet of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; of the <hi>Vnited Neitherlands,</hi> collected according to the charge &amp; order of the Lords <hi>States General.</hi> Dated the 24 June, 1666.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>By the Lords</hi> De Witt, <hi>Councill-Penſioner;</hi> Vrij<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergen, Van der Hoolck, Kann, <hi>&amp;</hi> Gerlacius, <hi>their Deputies &amp; Plenipotentiaries at preſent beeing in the</hi> Wielings, <hi>for expediteing &amp; over the Employ of the ſaid Fleete, after a curious examineing of the chief Officers, Commanders, &amp; Captaines of the foreſaid Fleete.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet upon the 1, 2, 3, 4, &amp; 5, of June ſucceſſively, with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral winds &amp; calmes beeing gotten to Sea out of the <hi>Texſell:</hi> And through contrary winds or calmes not beeing able before the 8. to ſett courſe accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to order given to approach the <hi>English</hi> Coaſt; were with ſayling, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of tides, &amp; driveing, on the 11. fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the morneing, advanced unto about ſeven or eight Leagues Eaſt South Eaſt from the <hi>Northforeland,</hi> beeing the point of <hi>England,</hi> which ſtretcheth out between the Channel &amp; River of <hi>London:</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet, through contrary wind &amp; ſtream, were neceſſitated to Anker.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150219:4"/>
            <p>The <hi>English</hi> [who with their Fleet ſome dayes before were ankered in the <hi>Downs,</hi>] on the foreſaid 11 June 1666. [probably upon intelligence of the approach of the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleete,] put to Sea from thence with their Fleete, about noone apro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ached neere the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet, which <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet beeing then all together were eighty three Ships ſtrong, namely Fregats men of warre, beſides adviſe Boates, Fireships &amp; other ſmall Veſſels; but by accident even before the beginning of the work, &amp; but one hour before the Battel began, one of the capital Ships of the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet, commanded by <hi>Colonell Gent,</hi> through ſtamping of the Sea, loſt firſt his Bowſprit &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oremaſt in the ſight of the enemy, &amp; beeing unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable by order of <hi>Gen. de Ruyter</hi> as Admiral &amp; chief Commander of the Fleet aforeſaid was ſent up to <hi>Holland,</hi> the aforeſaid <hi>Coll. Gent.</hi> beeing before gon over aboard the Ship of <hi>Cap. Godskens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>English Fleet</hi> as they then were told by the <hi>Neitherlanders,</hi> were about eighty ſayle ſtrong; it was judged one a clock in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoone when each began to fire at the other, the <hi>Neitherlanders</hi> Ships haveing before cutt their cables, becauſe it was impoſſible through the hollow Sea &amp; shortnes of time in any wyſe to gett their Ankors onboard. Both the Fleets therewith beeing under ſaile ſtood together over to the Southward the wind beeing <hi>W. S. W.</hi> by which meanes the Eſquadron of the L. Admirals <hi>Tromp,</hi> &amp; <hi>van Meppelen,</hi> to whom particularly was aſſigned the Reare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard (haveing lyen at an Anker to the South weſtward) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Vanguard. And he the ſaid L. Admirall <hi>Tromp</hi> shewed himſelfe valiant &amp; reſolute in the foremoſt &amp; heavieſt of the fight; &amp; hee was alſo manfully ſeconded by his <hi>Vice-</hi> &amp; <hi>Reare Admirals,</hi> &amp; other Officers. Whereupon immediately according to order the Eſquadron of <hi>Generalde Ruyter</hi> &amp; <hi>L. Admiral van Nes,</hi> fell in with the enemy &amp; with their chief Officers &amp; Captaines ſignally quitted themſelves. Preſently after about 3. or 4. a clock after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon an <hi>English</hi> Fregat of the <hi>Blew Eſquadron</hi> carryng by gheſſe 50. Guns, ſo ſoon as he was paſt the <hi>Gen. de Ruyters</hi> ſide having recieved from him the laſt ſalute ſunk a little a ſtern of him.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150219:4"/>
            <p>The Eſquadron of the <hi>L. Admiralls Cornelius Evertſon</hi> and <hi>Tjerck Hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des de Vries,</hi> could not at the firſt get up to the enemy, for that they were ſo farre to windward of them, whereby it was very fiercely fought on both ſides, each Fleet keeping the ſame courſe till about 5. of the clock in the aſtternoone, when the <hi>English</hi> having tacked made North Weſtward, and were the moſt part of them forced to beare up before the wind, as is judged to avoid the <hi>Flemmish Banks,</hi> &amp; then the Eſquadron of the <hi>Admiralls Cornelius Evertſon</hi> and <hi>Tjerck Hiddes de Vries,</hi> came alſo into a fierce combat whith the enemy, who likewiſe with their whole Eſquadron praiſe-worthyly and courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously quitted themſelves. And in the winding off of the <hi>English Fleet</hi> ſome of their leeward-moſt Ships were cut off, which were then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently boarded &amp; each by one <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ship overcome and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly brought up in <hi>Holland.</hi> The one named <hi>Swiftſure,</hi> mounted with 70. Guns, moſt of them braſſe &amp; commanded by <hi>Sir William Barckley, Vice-Admiral</hi> of the <hi>white Eſquadron,</hi> who (courageously de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending himſelfe againſt his overcomer, namely <hi>Henry Adrianſon,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the Ship <hi>Hern,</hi> mounted with 73 Guns) was in perſon ſlaine. The other named the <hi>ſeven Oakes,</hi> with abouth 60 Guns, was overcome by Capt. <hi>Vander Saen,</hi> commanding a Freggat of 52. Goteling. And the third named the <hi>Loyal George,</hi> with 44. Guns by <hi>Capt. Jacob Andreas Swart,</hi> commanding the Ship <hi>Deventer,</hi> mounted with 66. Guns, all three Captaines belonging to the Admiralty of <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> On the other hand in the firſt Attaque two <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ships the one named <hi>Duivenvoord,</hi> carrying 64. Guns, of which was Capt. the Young Heroe <hi>Otto van Treslong,</hi> &amp; the other named the <hi>Court of Zeeland,</hi> carrying 58. Guns, of which was <hi>Capt. Simon Block,</hi> both fell on fire as is judged by burneing tamkins shot out of their owne or other <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ships, by the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rce of the wind dryven back into the foreſaid Ships. In the aboveſaid Ship of <hi>Cap. Otto van Treslong,</hi> were the <hi>Prince of Monaco,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Earle of Guiſe,</hi> beeing carried on by a couragious zeal, who both of them happily &amp; in utmoſt perill were firſt ſaved in the Ship <hi>Small Holland</hi> upon which is Commander <hi>Capt. Evert van Gelder,</hi> Brother in the law to <hi>Gen. de Ruyter;</hi> &amp; after came over into the Ship of the foreſaid <hi>Gen. de Ruyter.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150219:5"/>
            <p>In the foreſaid Attaque was the Ship of L. Adm. <hi>Tromp</hi> found to bee ſo damaged in his Maſts, that by miſchance another <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ship comeing onboard him loſt all his Maſts; alſo the Ship of Reare Admirall <hi>van Nes</hi> about the ſame time had his Foremaſt shot by the board, ſo that both were neceſſitated as to their perſons to goe over into other Ships, where they againe let fly their reſpective Flaggs, &amp; as before with great valiantnes continued to doe their endeavour as formerly, &amp; the foreſaid maſtles Ships preſently according to orders given were ſent up &amp; towed out of the Fleet for <hi>Holland.</hi> The <hi>English</hi> as above having turned &amp; paſſing by the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet, their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall &amp; beſide him ſome other Ships of his Fleet came to an Anker, but shortly after ſeeing that <hi>Generall de Ruyter</hi> with his Fleet under him had alſo turned &amp; was comeing uppon him, they chopped their Cables &amp; there fell betwixt them a very hard &amp; heavy long-dureing fight; in which through Gods grace none of the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ships miſcarryed. But betwixt ſeven &amp; eight of the clock in the evening one more of the capitall <hi>English</hi> Ships of the Blew Eſquadron, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying by eſtimation betwixt 60. or 70. Guns, beeing paſt by the Ship of the <hi>Generall de Ruyter</hi> about a Musket shot, went to the ground; Both which <hi>English</hi> Ships ſunk cloſe by &amp; even amongſt the <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands</hi> Fleet, ſo as the ſame was perfectly ſeene by very many Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, Private Seamen &amp; Souldiers, beeing donne before their eyes &amp; remarqued by them; but it cannot certainly bee affirmed whether any other <hi>English</hi> Ships might be ſunke or deſtroyd that day: But towards evening the Reare Adm. of the White beeing a capitall Ship of war &amp; made very unſerviceable by <hi>Gen. de Ruyters</hi> &amp; others shot, there was commanded upon him one of the Fireships of the <hi>Gen. de Ruyters</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quadron, which being gotten onboard him &amp; preſently ſet on fire, the ſaid Fireship was forth with ſunke; whereupon a ſecond Fireship out of the <hi>Zeelands</hi> Eſquadron did likewiſe come onboard the ſaid R. Adm. and ſet him on fire but the ſaid R. Adm. cleared himſelfe &amp; each time found meanes to put out the fire in his Ship. A third <hi>Neither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Fireship under the favour of the Guns of the L. Adm. <hi>Cornelius E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertſon</hi> endeavouring to lay the ſaid R. Adm. onboard was before hee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150219:5"/>was faſt, shott to ground and ſunk, ſo that according to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing witneſs of all the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Officers which were there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, the often mentioned Reare Admirall of the White, with a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall conſtancy, as an honorable Souldier hath quitted himſelfe: And it is the more to be admired becauſe that [according to the witnes of ſome <hi>English</hi> Priſoners who leaped out of his ship into the ſea, &amp; were ſaved by the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ships at what time the forefaid two firſt Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reships came onboard him] beeing on fire, three hundred of his Seamen, accounting the matter deſperate (and to decline the fire) leaped over board, and choſe the water. Out of the foreſaid Reare Admirall in the evening late an unhappy shott was made which tooke out of the world the valiant L. Adm. <hi>Cornelius Evertſon,</hi> whoſe good conduct and courage in many foregoeing occaſions, as alſo in this was experimented; and thereuppon for that time was the fight parted by the Night, ſoe that through the darknes in the ſmook and damp, it could not bee marked whether the foreſaid Reare Adm. might be ſunk or have cleared and ſaved himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The Night beeing paſt the <hi>English</hi> Fleete on the 12 Iune 1666 with breake of Day was to windward above the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleete about a league &amp; halfe; the wind then beeing Weſt South Weſt, at which time both the Fleetes againe laid one towards the other, to wit, the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet Northweſt and the <hi>English</hi> South over: So ſoone as the two Fleetes, were approached nigh each other, the <hi>Neither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Fleete did alſo ly towards the South to ſtand the ſame courſe with the enemy. But the <hi>English</hi> ſetting aſide the advantage of the wind bore up uppon the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet and accordingly did run before the wind amongſt their enemies, the <hi>Neitherlanders</hi> keeping their courſe and bideing uppon a wind, running over againſt them, ſoe that both Fleets did in this manner paſſe with a heavy and sharp fight, without loſeing any one ſingle Ship of the <hi>Neitherlanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can any of the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Officers as yet give teſtimony to the <hi>Deputies</hi> and <hi>Plenipotentiaries,</hi> of the <hi>States Generall,</hi> that of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynty any of the <hi>English</hi> Ships were taken or deſtroid in the ſaid ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contre. The Fleets being paſt each other in this manner &amp; on both
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150219:6"/>ſides many Ships in their ſtanding &amp; running rigging much dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by shott, each with ſpliceing, wallknotting and otherwiſe againe ſought to make fitt, &amp; there uppon it beeing faln quite ſtill, both Fleets lay and drove in a calme till about 11. of the clock before noone: When the gale increaſing both Fleets laid towards each other (the <hi>Neitherlanders</hi> then beeing to Windward) and againe fell into a very furious fight. The <hi>Generallde Ruyter</hi> being advanced about halfe way in the <hi>English</hi> Fleete, heard in the midſt of the ſame very fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious shooteing, and from thence preſumeing that ſome Ships of the Fleete under him muſt bee in a ſtreight &amp; totally ſurrounded by the enemy reſolved with his Eſquadron under him to fall in; And hee preſently bearing up ran in amongſt the enemy, who uppon his comeing makeing ſome roome, hee ſaw and found that the <hi>L. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall Tromp,</hi> then in perſon beeing in and letting fly his flagg uppon the Ship of <hi>Jacob Cornelius Swart,</hi> had with a ſouldiers heart broken in there, and together with <hi>Vice- Admirall van der Hulſt, Captain Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Salomonſon, De Haen,</hi> and <hi>van Amstell,</hi> lay very much diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled ſurrounded by the enemy: All which without the aforeſayd ſuccor were in great danger to bee burned or ſunk, as indeed the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Ship of <hi>Peter Salomonſon</hi> was at the comeing of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſuccour already on fyre and thereby then loſt. The aforeſayd Captayn and a good part of his ſeamen were in utmoſt perill and juſt in their Extremity ſaved by the <hi>Neitherlanders;</hi> But it pleaſed God that hee (beeing gone over upon the Ship of Captayn <hi>Schey,</hi> and there according to his power doeing worthily,) dyed during the battell in the bed of honour.</p>
            <p>The aforeſaid Ship of <hi>Capt. Swart,</hi> &amp; of the aforenamed three other Captains, were, dureing the time of the ſaid ſurrounding made ſo unſerviceable, that the <hi>L. Admiral Tromp</hi> was neceſſitated again to goe over upon another Ship; And the aforenamed Ships of Vice-Admirall <hi>van der Hulst,</hi> &amp; the foreſaid <hi>Capt. de Haen, Swart</hi> &amp; <hi>van Amſtel,</hi> as being wholly unuſefull, muſt bee ſent up to the firſt &amp; fittingeſt heavens. In the aforeſaid throng amongſt others Vice-Admirall <hi>van der Hulst</hi> was alſo shot dead, who in all occaſions had
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150219:6"/>carryed &amp; leported himſelfe as a brave Souldier &amp; underſtanding Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer. Yet it pleaſed God the Lord in a short time doubly to repayr the foreſaid loſs &amp; dammage of the Ships of the States of the <hi>Vnited Neitherlands;</hi> for many of the <hi>English</hi> Fleet were the ſame day ſunk &amp; burned. Amongſt which there is remayning the perfect knowledge &amp; notice of theſe following Ships: Namely,</p>
            <p>Firſt, One of the Eſquadron of the <hi>Red,</hi> beeing according to gheſſe a Ship of about 60 Guns, ſunk about noon amongſt the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Ships or in the van of the <hi>English</hi> Fleet.</p>
            <p>Secondly, One of the Blew Eſquadron, carrying by gheſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 50 &amp; 60 Guns, ſunk about three of the clock in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, after hee had paſſed by <hi>General de Ruyter,</hi> &amp; in paſſing by him was duely ſaluted.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, One of the <hi>White</hi> Eſquadron, carrying according to gheſſe near 50 Guns, a little time after was ſunk by the ſyde of Vice-Admirall <hi>de Liefde,</hi> who had ſo boared him through with his Canon that he went to the ground.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, One of the Eſquadron of the <hi>White Flag,</hi> carrying about 50 Guns by computation, about halfe an hour after was ſunk in the Eſquadron of <hi>General de Ruyter,</hi> a little behind the Ship of <hi>Capt. van Meewen,</hi> who gave him a full lower tyre in paſſing by. And that it may certainly bee concluded that both the foreſaid Ships of the <hi>White</hi> Eſquadron, are two diſtinct Ships it is to be noted that many Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers &amp; ſeamen ſaw the one as wel as the other ruined: to wit, the ſame perſons that had ſeen the one ſunk ſaw the other ſunk alſo a short time after: whereof examination is carefully made to be ſure that one &amp; the ſame Ship should not bee taken for two diſtinct Ships.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The Ship the <hi>Black Eagle,</hi> or <hi>Armes of Groening,</hi> beeing the laſt Autumne (after that the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet by an heavy ſtorm were diſſipated from each other,) met by the <hi>English</hi> &amp; taken; which foreſaid Ship the <hi>Black Eagle</hi> was ſunk, <hi>Capt. Marrevelt</hi> having with fore-conſideration prepared &amp; fyred his whole broadſide upon it.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, Another <hi>English</hi> Ship ſunk in the middeſt of the <hi>English</hi> Fleet, after he had ſayled for ſome time with a Flag of diſtreſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mans comeing to his help.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150219:7"/>
            <p>In the aforeſaid two dayes as alſo in the fight of the fourth day (of with hereafter shall bee further ſpoken) there were undoubtedly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall English Ships burned of which nevertheleſſe no full certeynty of teſtimony can be given, in regard that ſome ſyre Ships were ſet on fyre &amp; yet it cannot bee perfectly ſaid whether the Ships which they were aboard of were burned or that they cleered themſelves. Except onely two <hi>English</hi> Ships, which many bee certainly affirmed dureing the fight to bee burned, one uppon the ſecond the other uppon the fourth day of the foreſaid Battel, for as much as the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Seamen that ſerved uppon the Fireships, come in with good certificates to obtaine their ſetled reward for that ſervice.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>English Priſoners</hi> fisht out of the Sea, and ſent to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Colledges of Admiraltyes, shall bee perfectly examined to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand out of what Ships they are particulary ſaved, undoubtedly yet more of the burned and ſunk <hi>English</hi> Ships will bee diſcovered.</p>
            <p>The Fight of the foreſaid 12. of Iune, was very fierce eſpecially in the afternoon, ſo that many Ships on both ſides were very much damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed in their Maſts, ropmaſts, ſayles &amp; rigging: Amongſt others about 3 or 4 of the clock in the afternoon was the main Topmaſt of <hi>Gen. de Ruyters</hi> Ship shott downe falling with Flagg &amp; pendant from above. Hee there uppon being ſomething unfitted gave order preſently to L. Admirall <hi>van Nes</hi> in meane while till that another Topmaſt should bee ſet againe to lett fly the pendent under his Flagg, &amp; for that time to acte as <hi>Generall,</hi> orderly to proſecute the fight. The which alſo was followed by him with ſuch courage &amp; conduct that both Fleets came up three times one towards the other that afternoon &amp; ſo hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſed each other towards the evening when the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> fleet had turned the fourth time toward the <hi>English</hi> they followed their courſe &amp; with all their ſayles made towards their owne coaſt; they body beeing leſſened toeight or nine &amp; thirty men of warre; the <hi>Neith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erlands</hi> Fleet ſtanding towards them (who were by their tacking got a good way aſterne,) did uſe all poſſible endeavour to fetch them up, to that end makeing all the ſayle they could. But the night &amp; calme co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meing up, were, next to Gods will, the cauſe that the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150219:7"/>could not reach them. The <hi>Gen. de Ruyter</hi> with his other ſailes ſo much as he could keepeing neer the Fleet got in the mean while his maine Topmaſt, Flagg &amp; pendant againe ſet up &amp; all brought into fitting poſture, &amp; did againe on the 13 his office as <hi>Generall.</hi> The <hi>English</hi> with breake of day diſcerneing that the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ships continued all poſſible endeavour to fetch them up, ſett their maſtles and ill ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Ships in fire, that they should not fall into the hand of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and uſed all meanes to fetch the <hi>River</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> ſetting to this end Topgallantſayles, Spritſayles, Lyſayles, &amp; Drabblers, yea alſo wet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Sailes &amp; ſetting all to worke that could any wayes further or help them, the wind then Eaſt &amp; afterwards Eaſt South Eaſt, with a ſmall gale. How many was the number of the Ships that for the cauſe above ſaid in the morneing were ſett on fire, could out of the <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands</hi> Fleet with no perfect certainty bee marked, the number beeing by one made greater than by another, but the <hi>English</hi> in their <hi>Gazette</hi> of 4/14 to 7/17 June 1666 printed at <hi>London</hi> by publique authority [wherein they adſcribe to themſelves the Victory,] ſay that 3 Ships dureing the retreat, by order from their <hi>Generall</hi> were ſet on fire, to wit, the Ship <hi>Saint Paul,</hi> &amp; two other ſlugg Ships, of which the names are not there printed. The foreſaid retreat continueing the whole day the <hi>English</hi> approached ſo neer the ſands lying before the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>River,</hi> that their <hi>Admirall</hi> of the <hi>White,</hi> named <hi>Sir George Aſcue,</hi> with the Ship <hi>Prince Royall</hi> under him, mounted with ninety Braſſe Guns beeing the biggeſt &amp; capitalſt Ship of their whole Fleet, came a ground uppon a certaine ſand named the <hi>Galper</hi> a grievous miſchance for a Souldier, who dureing the whole Battel had quitted himſelfe manfully, &amp; now not otherwiſe but according to order of his <hi>Generall</hi> was retireing; &amp; although the foreſaid <hi>Admirall</hi> in this manner being come a ground, made ſignes with shooting &amp; otherwiſe for helpe &amp; aſſiſtance yet nevertheleſſe all the Ships of the <hi>English</hi> Fleet &amp; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the reſt of his owne <hi>Eſquadron</hi> held their courſe: ſo that he beeing now alone bereft of force to reſiſt &amp; forſaken by all ſuccour should have been burned by two <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ships, which came preſently up to him, had not L. Admiral <hi>Tromp,</hi> being then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150219:8"/>uppon the Ship of Reare Admirall <hi>Sweers</hi> given ſignes to the aforeſaid Fireships to forbear, becauſe that uppon the Ship of <hi>Admirall Aſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Flagg was ſtrucken, &amp; ſo thereby as by other ſignes it was sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wd that quarter was deſired; vvhere uppon the Seamen of the aforeſaid Reare Admirall <hi>Sweers</hi> by order of I. Admirall <hi>Tromp</hi> vvent on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board the forenamed <hi>Aſcue,</hi> &amp; brought him over vvith ſome of his Officers &amp; people as Priſoners uppon the foreſaid R. Admirall <hi>Sweers,</hi> &amp; the next day in the morneing by order of <hi>Generall de Ruyter</hi> ſent the foreſaid <hi>Admirall Aſcue</hi> vvith a Galliot to the <hi>Hague,</hi> &amp; although the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Ship the <hi>Prince Royal</hi> aftervvards gott afloat againe, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe becauſe it vvould much incumber the Fleet <hi>Generall de Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ordered that the Ship should be burned, &amp; the People ſaved, which preſently vvas accordingly effected.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time towards the evening there came out of the Southweſt twenty two <hi>English</hi> Ships of warre, commanded, as was afterwards underſtood, by <hi>Prince Rupert,</hi> who as is now certified the day before vvas ſent off into the Channell &amp; there &amp; in the Haven of <hi>Portſmouth</hi> &amp; <hi>Plimmouth</hi> vvas to gather ſome more Ships to him &amp; ſo together to run &amp; meet the <hi>French Fleet</hi> under the Command of the <hi>Duke of Beaufort,</hi> &amp; attacque them. Likevviſe there came, out of the <hi>River of London</hi> as is judged, certainly from the <hi>English Coast,</hi> three other great Ships of vvarre, makeing together a nevv re-inforce of 25 good men of vvarre. The <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet ſeeing the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid nevv ſuccours to approach, the <hi>Zeeland</hi> &amp; <hi>Viieſland</hi> Eſquadron made tovvards them, but the aforeſaid body under <hi>Prince Rupert</hi>-decline them, &amp; ran tovvards the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet or the remainder of them, vvherevvith he conjoyned late in the evening. The vvhole <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Fleet beeing then in all with the foreſaid new Re-inforce ſixty or ſixty one good ships of vvarre ſtrong, vvhereof ſo notable a part vvere vvholly fresh ships. The <hi>Neitherlanders</hi> on the other hand vvere then together about ſixty four ships of vvarre, but all by a fight of tvvo dayes &amp; chaſe of the enemy the third day, much dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged &amp; tyred out, beeing but the remainder of their Fleet; three have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been ſunk or burned as is above related, others vvith their taken
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150219:8"/>priſes gon for <hi>Holland,</hi> others either maſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es or tovving maſtles ships ſent out of the Fleet. The matter novv ſtanding in theſe terms the <hi>Neitherlanders,</hi> vvhich novv ſavv a conſiderable Battel to bee expected having this night (to decline the ſands &amp; have more room) vvith a ſmall ſaile ſtretched Eaſtvvards on: The <hi>Generall de Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in the morneing early firſt called a <hi>Councill of Warre</hi> &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards alſo made a ſign to all his Captains to come aboard, &amp; having exhorted them all to doe their endeavour as alſo given them orders according to which they were to regulate themſelves, the Battel was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain begun the 14 of June forevvritten in the morneing about 8 of the clock, betvvixt the <hi>Foreland</hi> &amp; the <hi>Flemmſh Banks</hi> in the open ſea about 8 leagues from the Land, the Wind beeing South ſouth-eaſt, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet haveing the vveather gage did vvith their three Eſquadrons in three diſtinct places break into the enemy &amp; fought through them, wherewith the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were ſomewhat diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed. This beeing donne <hi>Generall de Ruyter</hi> tacked againe with the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet &amp; ſtood over Southwards towards the enemy, who on the other hand rallyed themſelves. This was re-iterated three ſeverall times diſtinctly, whereby it was fought neer this whole day very fiercely on both ſides with uncerteynty of the iſſue. Dureing this furious fight one of the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ships of warre commanded by Capt. <hi>Vytenhout</hi> was fyred &amp; after ſunk. One of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fireships ſeeing the Vice Admirall <hi>de Liefde</hi> diſabled &amp; lying with his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard downe, attempted to lay him on board; but was by the <hi>Vice-Admirall</hi> &amp; by Capt. <hi>William Bowdewijns</hi> turned off. Thereafter another <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fireship that by a shott was fired fell aboard that Fireship &amp; they burned both together. On the other ſide a <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship attempting to board and fire the Ship of <hi>Prince Rupert,</hi> the which in this short time was much battered, one of the <hi>English</hi> Fireships which attended on the foreſaid <hi>Prince</hi> came aboard the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> fireship &amp; thereby both the foreſaid fireships as alſo another <hi>English</hi> Ship which unhappily fell in with them were burned. In the meane while was the L. Admirall <hi>Tromp</hi> with the a forenamed Ship of Rear Admirall <hi>Sweers</hi> &amp; ſome other Ships with hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in a long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150219:9"/>&amp; furious fight with the enemy wholly diſenabled ſo that hee was forced with his foreſaid Ships to abide out of the fight that they might as much as was poſſible fit &amp; bring themſelves in poſture agayn. <hi>Gen. de Ruyter</hi> [although by this means the Fleet under him was dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished in a conſiderable number of capital Ships] nevertheleſſe ſeeing that the ſun began to grow low, reſolved [without tying himſelfe too much to the advantage of the wind] to make the appoynted ſign ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally &amp; together with all the Eſquadron to break in uppon the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Where uppon the L. Adm<hi rend="sup">s</hi> 
               <hi>van Meppelen, de Vries,</hi> together with Vice Adm<hi rend="sup">s</hi> 
               <hi>Banckert, Schram</hi> &amp; <hi>Coenders,</hi> as alſo the R. Adm. <hi>Brunysvelt</hi> &amp; all the Captaines which were to windward reſolutely breaking in &amp; every one doeing his endeavour, it fell out that the L. Adm. van <hi>Nes</hi> &amp; the Vice Admirall <hi>De Liefde</hi> with the R. Admirals van <hi>Nes</hi> &amp; <hi>Evert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> &amp; ſome others Ship beeing to lee-ward of the <hi>English</hi> Fleet &amp; the <hi>Generall de Ruyter</hi> with the reſt of the <hi>Neytherlands</hi> Ships to Windward; they ſo ſtreightned the middle of the <hi>English</hi> Fleete betwixt them both the ſayd Fleet beeing by this means attacqued both before &amp; behind, that the enemy after a sharp fight of an hour &amp; half, not willing as it ſeems to bee boarded by the <hi>Neitherlanders</hi> Ships, betook themſelves the ſecond time againe to flight &amp; thereby fell wholly into confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; rent in pieces. The <hi>White Flagg</hi> with eight or tenne <hi>English</hi> men of warre bore away before the wind northwards with leeſayles ſet, &amp; the <hi>Admiralls</hi> of the <hi>Red</hi> &amp; <hi>Blew Eſquadrons</hi> by the wind ran over towards the <hi>English</hi> coaſt hoyſing up all the ſayles that they could. The <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ships which uppon the aforeſaid ſignall of the <hi>Gen. de Ruyter</hi> could lay a board any <hi>English</hi> Ship, maſtered it: Amongſt others the R. Adm. <hi>Brunsvelt</hi> boarding two of the enemies Friggats that lay faſt together hee alone overcame both the foreſaid enemies Ships; But in this confuſion as appears took no ſufficient order for the keeping poſſeſſion of the two a foreſayd prizes, whereby the <hi>English</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards made themſelves maſters of them againe: but ſome time after Capt. <hi>Pawes</hi> obſerveing it, retook both the fore ſaid reſcued Ships; but the one named the <hi>Bull</hi> which could not longer keep the Sea nor bee brought in to any haven was ſoon ſunk, the other named the <hi>Eſſex,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150219:9"/>a faire Fregat with 58 guns not very much damaged is brought up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Texell.</hi> The like accident of beeing retaken is hapned to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>English</hi> prize. The Vice Admirall <hi>Coenders</hi> did at the ſame time overcome &amp; bring up accordingly into the <hi>Texell</hi> the Ship called the <hi>Clovetree</hi> mounted with 62 guns; which the laſt yeare was taken by the <hi>English</hi> from the State of the United <hi>Neitherlands.</hi> Likewiſe alſo Capt. <hi>Ruth Maximilliaen</hi> at the ſame time did maſter &amp; hath brought up into <hi>Goree</hi> the Ship named the <hi>Convertine</hi> mounted with 54 guns. Beſides theſe uppon the forewritten day according to the knowledge of the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Officers there were two <hi>English</hi> Ships ſunke, to witt, one of the Eſquadron of the <hi>White</hi> which ſunk in the evening, &amp; the other a little time thereafter, it beeing not without likely hood that more other <hi>English</hi> Ships are deſtroyd of which the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiers have not full knowledge and therefore of that particular no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can bee certainly affirmed by them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>English</hi> finding themſelves in this deſolate poſture &amp; follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Neitherlanders, God the Lord;</hi> [which by his almighty hand had brought the worke thus farre] as appears did not pleaſe that they should for that time bee brought into farther ruine, or fall in to the hands of the <hi>Neitherlanders.</hi> His <hi>Divine Majesty</hi> this evening about ſeven of the Clock very ſuddenly cauſed a thick miſt to come up, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reing the which the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet, having chaſed the enemy 4. glaſſes was at laſt forced to forbear the further proſecution, leaſt chaſeing the enemy upon uncerteynty &amp; as it were by groping they should ſcatter &amp; diſſipate themſelves, which acording to rules of Sea affayres should have been moſt unadviſedly don; yea not to bee anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered. Wherefore the <hi>Gen. de Ruyter</hi> by the ordinary ſign-shotts gathered the Fleet together, which lay driving with a ſmall ſayle the whole night, but the next day morneing beeing the 15 of June afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid noe <hi>English</hi> Ship could bee deſcryed no not from the topmaſts of the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Ships. The battel &amp; proſecution of it, there-with had an end: The <hi>Generall de Ruyter</hi> the ſame day with the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet beeing ſtrong ſixty Ships of warre arrived in the <hi>Wielings</hi> according to order, that beeing the rendezvous appoynted by the State.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:150219:10"/>
            <p>Nine others, beſide the forementioned Ship of <hi>Coll. Gent,</hi> beeing, part dureing the fight &amp; part after the end of the Battel, either unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable or come into <hi>Goree,</hi> to bring up their Prizes; Ten others for like reaſon ſucceſſively ſent towards the <hi>Texell</hi> as belonging thereto; And the remaining four were as is here above related burned or ſunk, making together 843 which with one light Fregat of the <hi>Maes</hi> uſed for an adviſe-boate, amounts to the number of 85 Ships of warre: which number the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Fleet did conſiſt of, beſydes Fireships, Adviſe-boates, &amp; other Veſſels when they ſet ſayle from before the <hi>Texell.</hi> And wee underſtand that the remainder of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet having endeavoured with all diligence to fetch ſeverall of the next Havens they could, did the moſt part of them get in at <hi>Harwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For which Victory the inhabitants of the <hi>Confoederate Neitherlands</hi> are bound to give the higheſt thankes unto God the Lord, who hath given them ſo eminent a Victory. For according to the ſtedfaſt &amp; conſtant witnes of the Officers that have been in the Fleet, &amp; alſo according to what appeares by bringing up of Priſes before our eyes, three &amp; twenty Ships of warre of the enemyes are ruined or taken &amp; brought up, &amp; amongſt them eſpecially one <hi>Admirall</hi> &amp; one <hi>Vice-Admirall,</hi> beſides thoſe which without the knowledge of the foreſaid <hi>Neitherlands Officers</hi> may be burned, ſunk, or come to other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chances: And on the contrary in a fight of four dayes no more then 4 <hi>Neitherlands</hi> Men of warre all of particular although valiant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines are loſt; &amp; not any thing thereof is faln into the enemies hands for their rejoyceing.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Thus Collected by the means &amp; in manner afore ſaid <date>this 26 of Iune 1666.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Was Signed <hi>T. Gerlacius.</hi>
               </signed> And under ſtood <hi>By order of the Deputyes &amp; Plenipotentiaryes aforeſaid. ſubſcribed,</hi>
               <signed>G. Borth.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150219:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
